<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[RobLav]]></title>
  <link href="http://roblav.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://roblav.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-22T15:55:43+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://roblav.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rob Lavender]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Omega 4]]></title>
    <link href="http://roblav.github.io/blog/2013/11/14/omega-4/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-14T16:16:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://roblav.github.io/blog/2013/11/14/omega-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Are you ready for Omega 4?</h2>

<p>Over the past couple of years I&rsquo;ve been using Omega 3 as my base theme of choice. It provides plenty of features to get up and running quickly; creating sub-themes using drush, exporting theme settings to the info file, thanks to Omega Tools.</p>

<p>Omega 3 provides the best in a combination of drush command line functions with a comprehensive user interface to make sure a lot of hard work is already done for you; easy toggle options for default css files, <del>responsive</del> adaptive web design available to turn on when required.</p>

<p>All of these features have made Omega 3 the de facto standard for a lot of Drupal themers.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>What about Omega 4?</h3>

<p>Omega 4 is a bold progression to keep Omega up to date with the latest in front end development best practices, using all that SASS and Compass have to offer. Currently it means to get the best out of the Omega 4 you will need to get your hands dirty in the command line. Which in my experience is not a bad thing at all.</p>

<p>I was at the Frontend United conference in London, April 2013, when I first heard about Omega 4, when I was chatting to Matt Smith; one of the maintainers of Omega 4. A lot of what he showed me went a little over my head, I wasn&rsquo;t particularly au fait with using Ruby gems and it seemed so far removed from Omega 3 even Matt questioned if it should be called Omega at all. Sam Richards (Snugug) was one of the speakers at the conference. His talk which included a demo of the Compass extensions Singularity and Breakpoint, which make creating grids and responsive design easier to manage, also had the same effect of peeking my interest in these new shiny tools.</p>

<p>After the conference I took a peak under the hood of Omega 4 and the Compass extensions Snugug highlighted, but at the time it was all a little bit too much for me to take on board. Anyway who has time to keep up with all the latest trends! Thankfully, over the last couple of months I&rsquo;ve had the opportunity to learn a few things about Ruby Version Manager, installing various ruby gems, playing a little with Angular JS and tractor, poking around in the Radix theme and getting a better understanding of how it uses Ruby Gems to add Twitter Bootstrap features. Plus, getting to grips with responsive web design, and understanding some of the common perils and pitfalls that are par for the course of creating responsive themes.</p>

<p>These other projects have given hands on experience of the future of web design and frontend development, and I could finally begin to see the bigger picture of how Omega 4 is embracing the future and is determined to provide Drupal themers with the tools for them to embrace it too!</p>

<p>Omega 4 is really a melting pot of many of the best frontend components all wrapped up in one package. The rest of this article is going to focus on the taking a closer look at each of those components to get a better understanding of how it all fits together.</p>

<h3>Assumptions</h3>

<p>Before we start there&rsquo;s a small caveat, you will need an understanding of Drush and SASS/Compass. I&rsquo;m not going to go in to any detail about these two. They have been around long enough that if you were using Omega 3 you should be familiar with Drush and SASS/Compass already.</p>

<h3>Omega 4</h3>

<p>First look at Omega 4 there are just 2 directories in the theme:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>ohm</strong> &ndash; A demo theme, placed in the main directory because of problems with inheritance.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>omega</strong> &ndash; The main Omega 4 theme, including the starterkits/default directory with is the basis for creating a sub-theme.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Note: Omega Tools module is no longer required as the core functionality this provided now comes as standard.</p>

<p><strong>Starterkits</strong></p>

<pre><code>startkits/default
</code></pre>

<p>Lets take a look under the hood of the default starter kit to get an idea of how it all works. This is what is included:</p>

<ul>
<li>RVM and Ruby Gems</li>
<li>Bundler</li>
<li>Susy or Singularity Grid System</li>
<li>Breakpoint</li>
<li>Toolkit</li>
<li>Polyfills</li>
<li>Guard or Grunt</li>
</ul>


<h2>What is RVM and Ruby Gems?</h2>

<p>It is recommended that to use Omega 4 you should use RVM (Ruby Version Manager). RVM will provide you with the ability to create a consistent environment for you and people you work with. One of the problems with using Ruby is as things get updated you may find you get conflicts, so to avoid any issues if everyone is using the same versions of all the Ruby Gems, for any particular project, then everything will work as expected. If you start a new project and you want to use the latest versions, no problem just create a new gem set and your good to go, you can switch from one project to the next and have it setup so you only ever use the correct gems for that project.</p>

<p>RVM comes with a set of default gems including &lsquo;bundler&rsquo;, &lsquo;rake&rsquo;, &lsquo;rubygems-bundler&rsquo; and &lsquo;dvm&rsquo; gems.</p>

<p>In Omega 4 Startkit there are 2 files for use with RVM:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>.ruby-gemset</strong> &ndash; This file contains the name of the RVM gem set to use.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>.ruby-version</strong> &ndash; This file contains the version of ruby to use.</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>Bundler</h3>

<p>RVM helps to have per project environments to make sure we are using the same version of ruby gems as other people we work with, where does Bundler fit in? Think of RVM being like a shopping bag that contains all our gems, Bundler is a shopping list that defines the gems that we want.</p>

<p>Lets take a look at 2 files in the Omega 4 directory, Gemfile and Gemfile.lock.</p>

<p><strong>Gemfile</strong></p>

<p>This provides a shopping list of all the Gems that are required for our project.</p>

<pre><code>  # Sass, Compass and extensions.
  gem 'sass'                        # Sass.
  gem 'sass-globbing'               # Import Sass files based on blobbing pattern.
  gem 'compass'                     # Framework built on Sass.
  gem 'compass-validator'       # So you can `compass validate`.
  gem 'compass-normalize'   # Compass version of normalize.css.
  gem 'compass-rgbapng'         # Turns rgba() into .png's for backwards compatibility.

  # Grid Frameworks
  gem 'susy'                        # Susy grid framework.
  gem 'singularity's'               # Alternative to the Susy grid framework.

  gem 'toolkit'                     # Compass utility from the fabulous Snugug.
  gem 'breakpoint'                  # Manages CSS media queries.
  gem 'oily_png'                    # Faster Compass sprite generation.
  gem 'css_parser'                  # Helps `compass stats` output statistics.

  # Guard
  gem 'guard'                       # Guard event handler.
  gem 'guard-compass'           # Compile on sass/scss change.
  gem 'guard-shell'                 # Run shell commands.
  gem 'guard-livereload'            # Browser reload.
  gem 'yajl-ruby'                   # Faster JSON with LiveReload in the browser.
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Gemfile.lock</strong></p>

<p>This file holds all of the specific version details to keep our environment consistent.</p>

<pre><code>GEM
  remote: https://rubygems.org/
  specs:
    addressable (2.3.5)
    breakpoint (2.0.5)
      compass (&gt;= 0.12.1)
      sass (&gt;= 3.2.0)
    chunky_png (1.2.8)
    color-schemer (0.2.5)
      compass (~&gt; 0.12)
      compass-blend-modes (~&gt; 0.0.2)
    compass (0.12.2)
      chunky_png (~&gt; 1.2)
      fssm (&gt;= 0.2.7)
      sass (~&gt; 3.1)
</code></pre>

<p>With these files in place all we need to run is:</p>

<pre><code># bundle install
</code></pre>

<p>This will download the specific versions of the Gems and add them to our RVM gem set.</p>

<h2>Singularity</h2>

<p><a href="https://github.com/Team-Sass/Singularity">https://github.com/Team-Sass/Singularity</a></p>

<p>Omega 4 is bundled with 2 grid systems, Susy and SingularityGS. Both offer similar features so choose one and go for it.</p>

<p>The benefits of using these grid systems is that instead of using class names, like &lsquo;grid-6&rsquo;, dotted around your HTML files you use the container structures that are already in place. The means that your grid is more semantic when developing with responsive in mind. As your view port gets smaller what tends to happen is at a mobile size the grid becomes 1 column. With a non-semantic grid your container will still have a class of &lsquo;grid-6&rsquo; but it&rsquo;s no longer spanning 6 columns it&rsquo;s spanning 1.</p>

<p>Rather than give a comprehensive overview of how Susy or SingularityGS work, I&rsquo;d recommend testing them out for yourself.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s how it an example of how to set up your sass file:</p>

<pre><code>@import "singularitygs";

$grids: 6;

body {
  @include background-grid; //Display the grid for debugging purposes
}

$grids: 1 1 1 1;

Singluarity works with breakpoint

$grids: 4;
$grids: add-grid(6 at 30em);
$grids: add-grid(12 at 50em);

Example

$grids: 12;

body{
  width: 90%;
  margin: 0 auto;
}

.l-page {
  @include background-grid;
}

.l-main{
  @include clearfix;
}

.l-content{
  @include grid-span(8, 5);
}

.l-region--sidebar-first{
  @include grid-span(4, 1);
}
</code></pre>

<h2>Breakpoint</h2>

<p><a href="https://github.com/Team-Sass/breakpoint">https://github.com/Team-Sass/breakpoint</a></p>

<p><a href="http://breakpoint-sass.com/">http://breakpoint-sass.com/</a></p>

<p>Use Breakpoint to write the media queries for you.</p>

<p>A major benefits of using breakpoint is the creation of a no media query css file to support IE8 and lower. Using mobile first we build layouts for mobiles and then build out for larger viewports. As IE8 and lower don&rsquo;t support media queries they would only get the mobile layout, but using SASS and breakpoint we can provide IE8 and lower with a special css file, added using conditional comments, that contains the correct layout styles.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s what it looks like in your sass file:</p>

<pre><code>$breakpoint-no-queries: true;
$breakpoint-no-query-fallbacks: false;

body {
  background: dodger blue;
  @include breakpoint(567px, $no-query: true) {
    background: green;
  }
}
</code></pre>

<h2>Toolkit</h2>

<p><a href="https://github.com/Team-Sass/toolkit">https://github.com/Team-Sass/toolkit</a></p>

<p>There&rsquo;s too much to list, go check it out.</p>

<h2>Polyfills</h2>

<p>Omega 4 gives you the option of several polyfills to force older browsers to work with the latest techniques.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>selectivizr</p></li>
<li><p>html5shiv</p></li>
<li><p>respond</p></li>
<li><p>matchmedia</p></li>
<li><p>pie</p></li>
</ul>


<p>There are 2 options to get these polyfills into your theme either using drush make or Bower</p>

<p><strong>Make file </strong> &ndash; libraries.make</p>

<p><strong>Bower</strong> &ndash; .bowerrc, bower.json</p>

<p><strong>Creating a Sub-theme</strong></p>

<p>If you use RVM and Drush when you create a sub-theme the polyfills are automatically downloaded and added for you.</p>

<h2>Guard or Grunt</h2>

<h3>Guard</h3>

<p>Guard provides automation for some features such as automatically compiling your sass files, reloading the browser, clearing Drupal theme cache. Guard makes your theme development quicker.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/guard/guard">https://github.com/guard/guard</a></p>

<p><strong>Guardfile</strong> &ndash; This file holds the configuration for Guard.</p>

<p><strong>Note:</strong> To use guard make sure you enable the live reload browser plugin</p>

<h3>Grunt</h3>

<p>Grunt also provide what Guard does and more, but requires Node.js so is harder to get working.</p>

<p><strong>Gruntfile.js</strong> &ndash; This file holds the configuration for Grunt.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Taking this whistle stop tour of Omega 4 should give you a good idea of all of the different component parts of this base theme, and will hopefully encourage you to take it for a spin. Initially all that Omega 4 has to offer can be a little daunting, but once you begin to break things down and look at some of the components on there own you&rsquo;ll soon be using these tools for other projects that may or may not involve Omega 4 or Drupal.</p>

<h2>Helpful resources</h2>

<p><a href="https://drupal.org/node/1768686">Omega 4 Theme Documentation Handbook</a>
The documention is a the best place to start. If all the new fandangled things like using Ruby is new to you make sure you read <a href="https://drupal.org/node/1936970">Setting up a proper front-end development stack</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CmTuvzbPduI">Omega 4.x Demonstration w/Sebastian aka fubhy</a></p>

<p>3 hour demonstration, quite long well worth watching for a full overview of Omega 4.</p>

<p><a href="https://vimeo.com/69736259">Omega 4: Introduction by Matt Smith co-maintainer</a></p>

<p>Unfortunately not very good quality, so if you can get along, to his talk at Manchester Drupal Camp in November 2013. (Or probably more realistically watch it online afterward.)</p>

<p><a href="http://munich2012.drupal.org/program/sessions/responsive-design-sass-compass-and-drupal-7.html">Responsive Design with Sass+Compass</a></p>

<p>Really good overview of a lot of great SASS extensions that are provided in Omega 4. This is same presentation that I saw at Frontend United.</p>

<p><a href="http://screencasts.org/episodes/how-to-use-rvm">Using RVM</a></p>

<p>Watch this video to get an overview of RVM and why you should use it.</p>

<p><a href="https://vimeo.com/63509346">Singularity</a></p>

<p><a href="http://net.tutsplus.com/tutorials/tools-and-tips/guard-is-your-best-friend/">Guard</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CSS Generated Content]]></title>
    <link href="http://roblav.github.io/blog/2013/10/25/css-generated-content/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-25T16:44:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://roblav.github.io/blog/2013/10/25/css-generated-content</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://roblav.github.io/images/css-gen-content-1.jpg" title="Examples of CSS Generated Content" ></p>

<p>Generated content is content that can be added via css. The content doesn&rsquo;t appear in the DOM but is
visable on the page to the user. For this reason generated content is perfect for design embelishments,
but not good for user required content, as anyone using IE7 or older won&rsquo;t be able to see it.</p>

<p>The other advantages are there is one less request to the server if it replaces an image on the page,
and CSS shapes and Unicode entities can be scaled, unlike bitmap images.</p>

<h3>How does it work</h3>

<p>Use the :before or :after pseudo class to make use of the content property.</p>

<pre><code>div:after {
    content: "";
}
</code></pre>

<p>If you use a clearfix class to clear floats, you&rsquo;ve probably already used generated content.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<pre><code>.clearfix:after {
  content: "";
  display: table;
  clear: both;
}
</code></pre>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Shapes Demo</h3>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a <a href="http://roblav.github.io/demo/css-generated-content.html">demo</a> of the shapes you can create.</p>

<p>Find out about all the crazy cool CSS content you can create &ndash; <a href="http://css-tricks.com/pseudo-element-roundup/">http://css-tricks.com/pseudo-element-roundup/</a></p>

<h3>Unicode entities</h3>

<p>Look at all these fun unicode entities you can use.</p>

<div style="font-size: 6em;">♞ ☂ ★ ❤</div>


<p>Find lots of nice Unicode to use here <a href="http://copypastecharacter.com">copypastecharacter.com</a> and here <a href="http://unicode-table.com">unicode-table.com</a></p>

<p>You can copy and paste the entity directly as it is ♞ or you can convert it to a CSS Hex value using <a href="http://www.evotech.net/articles/testjsentities.html">Entity Conversion Calculator</a></p>

<blockquote><p>CSS &lsquo;content&rsquo; does not accept named entities or regular numeric entities such as &#64;, but does render ASCII text and unicode.
<a href="http://www.evotech.net/blog/2007/04/named-html-entities-in-numeric-order/">~ evotech.net &ndash; Using Unicode</a></p></blockquote>

<h3>Examples</h3>

<ul>
<li>Tooltip</li>
<li>Contact detail icons</li>
<li>CSS Shapes</li>
<li>CSS Ribbon</li>
</ul>


<h3>Support:</h3>

<p>IE8+ (IE6 &amp; 7 don&rsquo;t support the :before :after pseudo class)</p>

<h3>Further reading:</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.standardista.com/css3/creating-counters-with-generated-content/">standardista.com &ndash; Generated content</a></p>

<h4>&mdash;Update Nov 2013</h4>

<p>It&rsquo;s worth checking which Unicode entities are available for devices like iPad, if you&rsquo;re wanting your site to look good for those devices. I recently found this out while developing a site and the Unicode characters that I was using weren&rsquo;t available. The results weren&rsquo;t great. The easiest way to check is by viewing <a href="http://unicode-table.com">unicode-table.com</a> on the device and you can easily see which characters are available.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p><a href="http://nicolasgallagher.com/micro-clearfix-hack/">http://nicolasgallagher.com/micro-clearfix-hack/</a><a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SASS Project setup]]></title>
    <link href="http://roblav.github.io/blog/2013/10/25/sass-project-setup/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-25T08:57:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://roblav.github.io/blog/2013/10/25/sass-project-setup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>.gitignore</h2>

<pre><code>.sass-cache
</code></pre>

<h2>config.rb</h2>

<pre><code>environment = :production


# You can select your preferred output style here (can be overridden via the command line):
# output_style = :expanded or :nested or :compact or :compressed

output_style = (environment == :development) ? :expanded : :compressed
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Responsive Web Design in Drupal]]></title>
    <link href="http://roblav.github.io/blog/2013/10/01/Responsive-Web-Design-in-Drupal/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-01T13:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://roblav.github.io/blog/2013/10/01/Responsive-Web-Design-in-Drupal</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post is coming off the back of a presentation that I recently gave at my local Drupal meet up. This is an opportunity for me to review that presentation and consolidate some of my thoughts.</p>

<p>As I was preparing I quickly realised that a 1 hour presentation about RWD in Drupal was only really ever going to scratch the surface. My primary objective was to give the audience a brief primer about RWD and then open up the discussion about our collective knowledge and experience.</p>

<h2>Ethan Marcotte &ndash; Responsive Web Design</h2>

<p>Responsive web design really started from an <a href="http://alistapart.com/article/responsive-web-design">article on A List Apart</a> by Ethan Marcotte in 2010. He basically outlined 3 main components for RWD, which are:</p>

<ul>
<li>Fluid grids</li>
<li>Flexible images</li>
<li>Media queries</li>
</ul>


<p>I’d also recommend Ethan’s book on RWD &ndash; <a href="http://www.abookapart.com/products/responsive-web-design">http://www.abookapart.com/products/responsive-web-design</a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Something to bare in mind there are myriad of overlapping techniques that will often be discussed using umbrella term responsive web design; mobile first, progressive enhancement, graceful degredation. There are differences between each of these strategies so it&rsquo;s worth finding out about them and experimenting to find out the best mix for you.</p>

<h2>Adaptive vs responsive</h2>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Fixed</strong> websites have a set width and resizing the browser or viewing it on different devices won’t affect on the way the website looks.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Fluid</strong> websites are built using percentages for widths. As a result, columns are relative to one another and the browser allowing it to scale up and down fluidly.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Adaptive</strong> websites introduce media queries to target specific device sizes, like smaller monitors, tablets, and mobile.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Responsive</strong> websites are built on a fluid grid and use media queries to control the design and its content as it scales down or up with the browser or device.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><a href="http://teamtreehouse.com/library/websites/build-a-responsive-website/introduction-to-responsive-web-design/fixed-fluid-adaptive-and-responsive">Source</a></p>

<p>Read this article for an in depth overview &ndash; <a href="http://uxdesign.smashingmagazine.com/2012/11/08/ux-design-qa-with-christian-holst">http://uxdesign.smashingmagazine.com/2012/11/08/ux-design-qa-with-christian-holst</a></p>

<h2>Grids</h2>

<p><a href="http://sonspring.com/journal/960-grid-system">960gs</a> &ndash; The 960 Grid System has been around since 2008. It’s the grid system I’m most familiar with because that’s what the Omega grid system is based on. It doesn’t really matter which grid system you use, as long as you understand the principles behind using a grid system and it’s limitations.</p>

<p>Before tackling grids on a website it’s well worth understanding a little bit of history about how grids have been used in graphic design. Two fantastic sources of information are <a href="http://www.markboulton.co.uk/journal/five-simple-steps-to-designing-grid-systems-part-1">Mark Boulton</a> and <a href="http://grids.subtraction.com/">Khoi Vihn</a>.</p>

<p><a href="960%20grid%20generator%20http://bit.ly/14yuE6G">960 Grid Generator</a> &ndash; A fantastic online resource for quickly understanding different grids.</p>

<h3>Grids in Omega</h3>

<p>Omega comes with a whole host of <a href="http://drupalcode.org/project/omega.git/tree/refs/heads/7.x-3.x:/omega/panels/layouts">panel layouts</a> out of the box for 12, 16 and 24 column layouts, and if any of them don’t quite suit your needs then creating your own versions as part of your sub-theme is pretty straight forward. <a href="http://zugec.com/blog/83-custom-grid-panels-layout-omega-theme">Omega Panel tutorial</a>.</p>

<p>Here’s some sample code of what a grid layout looks like:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
<span class='line-number'>24</span>
<span class='line-number'>25</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>&lt;div class="container-12 clearfix"&gt;
</span><span class='line'>  &lt;div class="grid-4"&gt;
</span><span class='line'>    &lt;!-- Content here --&gt;
</span><span class='line'>  &lt;/div&gt;
</span><span class='line'>  &lt;div class="grid-4"&gt;
</span><span class='line'>    &lt;!-- Content here --&gt;
</span><span class='line'>  &lt;/div&gt;
</span><span class='line'>  &lt;div class="grid-4"&gt;
</span><span class='line'>    &lt;!-- Content here --&gt;
</span><span class='line'>  &lt;/div&gt;
</span><span class='line'>  &lt;div class="grid-4"&gt;
</span><span class='line'>    &lt;!-- Content here --&gt;
</span><span class='line'>  &lt;/div&gt;
</span><span class='line'>  &lt;div class="grid-12"&gt;
</span><span class='line'>    &lt;div class="grid-12 alpha omega"&gt;
</span><span class='line'>      &lt;!-- Content here --&gt;
</span><span class='line'>    &lt;/div&gt;
</span><span class='line'>    &lt;div class="grid-6 alpha"&gt;
</span><span class='line'>      &lt;!-- Content here --&gt;
</span><span class='line'>    &lt;/div&gt;
</span><span class='line'>    &lt;div class="grid-6 omega"&gt;
</span><span class='line'>      &lt;!-- Content here --&gt;
</span><span class='line'>    &lt;/div&gt;
</span><span class='line'>  &lt;/div&gt;
</span><span class='line'>&lt;/div&gt;</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h2>Flexible Images</h2>

<p><a href="http://unstoppablerobotninja.com/entry/fluid-images/">http://unstoppablerobotninja.com/entry/fluid-images/</a></p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>img {
</span><span class='line'>  max-width: 100%;
</span><span class='line'>}
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>img,
</span><span class='line'>object {
</span><span class='line'>     max-width: 100%;
</span><span class='line'>}</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<blockquote><p>&ldquo;This solved the problem beautifully. Instead of just rendering at its native width and overflowing its containing box, the image would render at its native dimensions as long as its width didn’t exceed the width of its container.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<hr />

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;Modern browsers are intelligent enough to keep the image’s proportions intact, even as the page scales up or down accordingly. And as it turns out, this works just fine for most embedded videos, too:&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>IE</strong></p>

<blockquote><p>“Older versions of Internet Explorer don’t support max-width. So for especially large images, I’ve been relying on a simple width: 100% rule in an IE-specific stylesheet.”</p></blockquote>

<h2>Media Queries</h2>

<p>Media queries can be used within a link statement or directly within the CSS file.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>&lt;link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css"
</span><span class='line'>  media="screen and (max-width: 480px)"
</span><span class='line'>  href="shetland.css" /&gt;</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>




<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>@media screen and (max-width: 480px) {
</span><span class='line'>  .column {
</span><span class='line'>    float: none;
</span><span class='line'>  }
</span><span class='line'>}</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h2>Doing it with Drupal</h2>

<p><strong>Themes</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Omega</li>
<li>Zen</li>
<li>Adaptive</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Mobile Menu</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Responsive navigation</li>
<li>Responsive menu</li>
<li>Tiny Nav</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Flexible images</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Responsive images and styles</li>
<li>Adaptive images</li>
<li>Picture</li>
<li>Breakpoints</li>
<li>FitVids</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Responsive slideshow</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>FlexSlider</li>
<li>Adaptive images</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Misc.</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Layout</li>
</ul>


<h2>Other things to consider</h2>

<p><strong>Flexible typography</strong></p>

<p><strong>Adaptive JS</strong> &ndash; Only load the css that is required. With breakpoints the css files are loaded anyway.</p>

<p><strong>Touch target</strong> &ndash; 44px by 44px</p>

<p><strong>No hover state</strong> &ndash; Don’t hide content</p>

<p><strong>Retina display</strong></p>

<p><strong>Font sizes: px em rem</strong> &ndash; <a href="http://aralbalkan.com/notes/responsive-pixels/">http://aralbalkan.com/notes/responsive-pixels/</a></p>

<p><strong>Flow Type</strong> &ndash; <a href="http://simplefocus.com/flowtype/">http://simplefocus.com/flowtype/</a></p>

<p><strong>Nested grids</strong></p>

<p><strong>Testing</strong></p>

<p><strong>Ish</strong> &ndash; <a href="http://bradfrostweb.com/demo/ish/">http://bradfrostweb.com/demo/ish/</a></p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>&lt;meta name="viewport" content="initial-scale=1"&gt;</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p><strong>Stop using Drupal!</strong></p>

<p>The best way to learn about RWD is to stop using Drupal. Create some basic html pages and start testing the JavaScript libraries, typically a lot of Drupal modules like responsive-navigation, adaptive-images are ports of these scripts. It’s helpful to find out about them first hand.</p>

<h2>Additional Reading</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://bradfrost.github.io/this-is-responsive/patterns.html">http://bradfrost.github.io/this-is-responsive/patterns.html</a></li>
<li><a href="http://bradfrost.github.io/this-is-responsive/resources.html">http://bradfrost.github.io/this-is-responsive/resources.html</a></li>
<li><a href="http://blog.cloudfour.com/css-media-query-for-mobile-is-fools-gold">http://blog.cloudfour.com/css-media-query-for-mobile-is-fools-gold</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
